<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached the 11. of May 1652. In Taunton, upon the occasion of their great deliverance, received upon that day. / By George Newton Master of Arts, and minister of Gods word in that place.</title>
            <author>Newton, George, 1602-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N1046</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E670_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207038</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866113</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866113</idno>
            <idno type="VID">166226</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89667)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 166226)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 103:E670[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached the 11. of May 1652. In Taunton, upon the occasion of their great deliverance, received upon that day. / By George Newton Master of Arts, and minister of Gods word in that place.</title>
                  <author>Newton, George, 1602-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Roybould at the Unicorne in Pauls Church-yard London; and are to be sold by George Treagle in Taunton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 16".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:166226:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached the 11. of <hi>May</hi> 1652. IN TAVNTON, UPON The Occaſion of their great Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, received upon that Day.</p>
            <p>BY GEORGE NEWTON Maſter of Arts, and Miniſter of Gods Word in that Place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Roybould</hi> at the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nicorne</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard <hi>London;</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>George Treagle</hi> in <hi>Taunton.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:166226:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:166226:2"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Ezra 9.13, 14.</bibl>
                  <p>Seeing that thou our God haſt puniſhed us leſſe then our, &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>THe wickedneſſe of Iſrael in matching with the daughters of a ſtrange God, after the Lord had ſharply puniſhed them, and then delivered them again by a miracle of Mercy; was the occaſion of theſe words. The whole ſtory certifies us, that when the time of their Captivity in Babilon was expired and run out, God wonderfully ſtirred up the heart of <hi>Cyrus</hi> firſt, and after of <hi>Darius,</hi> to make a Proclamation and Edict, by which the Jews (who then were Captives under their Dominions) were permitted to return, to ſetle in their own Country, to repair the deſolation of the Temple, and therefore to re-erect and re-eſtabliſh the worſhip of the Lord amongſt them. An incomparable mercy if we conſider whence they were delivered, and to what they were reſtored, and ſuch as ſhould have been a ſtrong en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, and mighty obligation to obedience. But alas! it proved not ſtrong enough for their Corruptions, for they no ſooner were again replanted in the Land of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> but they turned aſide from God, and waxing wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton with their Peace and Mercy, joyned themſelves in Marriage with the people of the Lands, that were about them, and mingled the prophane and holy Seed together, which Ezra being made acquainted with, he was excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly affected with it, ſo that he rent his cloaths and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:166226:3"/>
tore away the hair of his head and of his beard, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpent his ſpirits in a holy paſſion, he ſate down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed; untill at length returning out of this amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he betakes himſelf unto the Lord in prayer, and there exceedingly bewailes the peoples ſin, and manifeſts withall a horrid apprehenſion of it, if they ſhould yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain return to their old abominations, which it ſeems he much feared; <hi>Seeing that thou our God haſt puniſhed us leſſe then, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two things we have eſpecially to be conſidered in the words, Firſt, a rare and eminent Mercy acknowledged, <hi>Our God hath puniſhed us leſſe then our Iniquities deſerve,</hi> and given us ſuch a deliverance as this. And then a hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible abuſe ſuppoſed, ſhould we againe break thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments: in the ſame kinde, and in the ſame degree, in ſuch a manner and in ſuch a meaſure as before. I doe not ſay we ſhall, but if we ſhould, what then? Why then our condition would be deſparat, there would be no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility almoſt of an evaſion? Wouldſt not thou be angry with us, till thou hadſt conſumed us, that there ſhould be no remnant nor eſcaping? There are a remnant of us yet, but then thou wouldſt deſtroy that remnant too, and ſo there would be none left. In the mercy acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged you may take notice with me of theſe two parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſomething Negative or Privative, the withhold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of evill: <hi>Seeing that thou our God haſt puniſhed us leſſe then our iniquities deſerve?</hi> Puniſhed us thou haſt indeed by our cruel enemies, but not to the extent and latitude of our deſerts. Then ſomething poſitive, the beſtowing of good, and given us ſuch a deliverance as this: Not bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a deliverance onely, but ſuch deliverance, ſuch as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be expreſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:166226:3"/>So that you ſee my Brethren, here is mercy upon all hands, mercy in the puniſhment, mercy in the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from it; mercy in the puniſhment, that it was ſuch, ſo little, mercy in the deliverance from it, that it was ſuch, ſo great: Mercy in the puniſhment, that it was infinitely leſſe mercy in the deliverance, that it was infinitely more then they deſerved. All the wayes of God are mercy and truth, mercy not onely when he ſaves, but mercy when he ſtrikes his people: When he ſtrikes he doth ſo little, and when he ſaves he doth ſo much: when he ſtrikes he is ſo gracious, and when he ſaves he is ſo glorious, that he is wonderfull in both theſe.</p>
            <p>Well then my brethren, here is a Treble and a Baſe, to make you muſick on this ſolemn Day of Joy; the one is very low, and the other very high: The puniſhment is very low and flat, abundantly below their ſins, beneath their merits and deſerts. But the deliverance on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide is high and ſhril, indeed above Ela, Such as the Prophet cannot reach in his expreſsion; and therefore mentions it in ſuch a manner, that he leaves it rather to be wondered at, then diſtinctly underſtood. And given us ſuch a deliverance as this. Theſe two my brethren will doe very well together, though they be of divers ſounds, yet if we joyn them, they will make a good concord. And therefore that I may not marre the muſick, you ſhall hear them go together; and out of both, I ſhall raiſe this obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctr.</hi> It is the manner of the Lord when he puniſheth his people, to abate and to be very moderate, when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers them and ſhews them mercy, to exceed and to tranſcend all meaſure.</p>
            <p>Both theſe you ſee are ſet together in my Text, that ſo the one of them might ſound the better for the other: <hi>Seeing thou our God haſt puniſhed us leſſe then our iniquities
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:166226:4"/>
deſerve, and given us ſuch a deliverance as this:</hi> The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet layes the puniſhment and the deliverance ſide by ſide, that you may look upon them both at once, and compare both together, that you may ſee the ſmalnes of the one and the greatneſſe of the other: For if you mark it well, he ſets a ſpeciall emphaſis on the Deliverance, no emphaſis at all on the Affliction. The puniſhment is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of by way of diminution and abatement in a leſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing way, <hi>leſſe then our iniquities deſerve:</hi> But the deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on the other ſide, is ſpoken of by way of augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and enlargement, <hi>ſuch a deliverance as this.</hi> I ſhall proceed with both the branches of the text and point in order.</p>
            <p>It is the manner of the Lord when he puniſhes his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to abate and to be very moderate. There hath been a queſtion ſtarted in theſe latter dayes, whether the Lord at any time in any caſe doth puniſh his people. And true it is, he doth not neither can he puniſh them in a way of Vindication or revenge, for Chriſt hath fully ſatisfyed for them.</p>
            <p>But he is often ſaid to puniſh then in ſcripture in a way of caſtigation and correction: So the Original, is renderd in my text thou haſt puniſhed us ſaith <hi>Ezra.</hi> And for my own part, becauſe I am not ſo farre skilled in the Hebrew, as to adventure to controule the tranſlatours of the Bible; I allow of that expreſſion in the ſenſe before mentioned. And ſo I ſhould adviſe all thoſe to doe, who have no better skill then I have.</p>
            <p>Well, when the Lord doth puniſh or correct, or chaſten his people (call it how you will) it is his manner to abate, and to be very moderate; to do too little, rather then too much; to do rather leſſe then more; <hi>Leſſe then their iniquities deſerve,</hi> as you have it in my text. He often laies on many ſtripes under, never one ſtripe over. Never
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:166226:4"/>
more then we <hi>deſerved:</hi> When he is ſharpeſt, we muſt acknowledge with the Church, that he hath not rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us according to our ſins. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.10. Never more then we <hi>can bear,</hi> for the Lord knoweth whereof we are made, remembreth that we are but duſt. He underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth very well how weak we are, and therefore he debates with the affliction, as the Prophet ſpeakes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.8. whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be too heavy for us, yea or no, and if he finde it be, if he perceive the ſtorm of wrath to blow too rough up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his people, he ſtaies his rough wind, in the day of the Eaſt-winde, as it is added there in that place. Nay, my beloved, as he never gives us more in a correcting way, then we deſerve, never more then we can bear, ſo never more then we <hi>do need.</hi> If need be, we are in heavineſs, as the Apoſtle in that known place, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.6. God never laies a ſtroak, a trial, an affliction more then needs upon his people. He alwayes keeps himſelf within compaſſe: And therefore he is ſaid to <hi>ſpare</hi> his people according to his promiſe, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17.</p>
            <p>There is a twofold mercy oppoſed to the ſtrictneſs of a twofold Juſtice, with which the rigour and exactneſſe of it is qualified and allayed. Either <hi>miſericordia parcens,</hi> or, <hi>remunerans,</hi> either ſparing, or remunerating mercy. The exactneſs of Juſtice in diſpenſing recompences, is tempered with <hi>remunerating mercy,</hi> when there is more beſtowed on men then they deſerve: The rigour of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in diſpenſing puniſhments, is qualifyed with <hi>ſparing mercy,</hi> when there is leſſe inflicted upon men then they deſerve. And this God alwayes exerciſes in the corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that he laies upon his people, he tempers them with ſparing mercy; he ſtaies his hand, and refrains his indignation. It is his manner to abate, and to be very moderate, as you have heard. That Phraſe of the Apoſtle in another caſe, may be applyed to God in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:166226:5"/>
this particular, his <hi>moderation</hi> is known to all men. And it is ſingularly known to you the people of this place, how he qualified his wrath in all the late afflictions, that have been upon you: ſo that you muſt confeſſe with <hi>Ez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> in my Text, That he hath puniſhed you far leſſe then your iniquities deſerved. And there are many reaſons of the point, I ſhall touch the principal.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And firſt of all, to ſay the truth, he hath no minde to puniſh or correct at all; ſo that it is no wonder, though he be very moderate in his corrections, he afflicts not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, nor grieves the ſons of men. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.33. He hath no will at all to do it, no of himſelf he delights in ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy, <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.18. The act of Juſtice is a little ſtrange to him, what the act of Mercy is? for he is <hi>rather,</hi> though <hi>not more</hi> mercifull then juſt; and hence he ſtileth it, his <hi>ſtrange act,</hi> which he is not ſo well acquainted with, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.21. It is not with our heavenly, as it is often, with our earthly parents; they correct us for their pleaſure, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.10. to ſatisfie their humour, and their paſſion, and the like. So doth not God, he takes no pleaſure to afflict us; no, his delight and pleaſure is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be ſhewing mercy. You may obſerve how loath he is to deal againſt us, and how unwillingly he takes us up to laſh us, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.8. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up Ephraim, how ſhall I deliver thee Iſrael, &amp;c.</hi> That hand cannot be cruel in correction, that takes the rod with ſuch abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant reluctation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When he is forced to correct us, he doth it in a good temper, and that is another reaſon, why he is ſo mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate: He corrects us not in anger, at leaſt not in the heat of his anger, which hath no meaſure in it, no mixture of compaſſion with it, which is the thing the Prophet prayes againſt, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.25. but with judgement, that you
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:166226:5"/>
with ſerious counſell, and mature deliberation, as is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp;c. he is not like a furious man ſtriketh, and on a ſuddain and in a rage, and felleth to the ground, never conſidering with him ſelf, whether the blow be is about to reach, be fitted and proportioned to the ſtrength of him that is to under go it, yea or no: No he chaſtens his with judgement and advice: He doth it in a ſettled and compoſed way, he is not angry, at leaſt, but a <hi>little angry.</hi> When he deals againſt the wicked, he is <hi>ſore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed</hi> at them, as his own expreſsion is, <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.15. but he is but a little angry with his own people, as is added, &amp;c. and becauſe he is angry but a little, he corrects them but a little.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Lord is very moderate; becauſe as he corrects his people in little anger, ſo in great love: They may look up and ſee him ſmiling, when he layes upon them; when he is moſt ſevere and bitter with his people, his kindeneſſe to them works ſtill, according to that ſweet and precious promiſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.31. <hi>If his children forſake, &amp;c. Then will I viſite their tranſgreſſions, &amp;c.</hi> If he be in a little heat at any time, he recollects himſelf again, and in the midſt of wrath remembers mercy, as the Prophet ſpeaks, and tempers it with this allay; he conſiders with himſelf, as once he did with Ephraim, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.20. <hi>Is not this my own ſon, is he not my pleaſant childe, whom I am lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on upon.</hi> And ſhall I uſe my own ſweet child thus? Shall I ſhew him no compaſsion? With that his bowels turn within him, and he ſaith, that he will ſurely have mercy upon him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When he puniſheth his people it is his manner to abate, and to be very moderate, becauſe he aims not at revenge, but reformation. Indeed revenge will have the moſt in a buſines, it will have full and perfect ſatisfaction,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:166226:6"/>
he will not ſpare in the day of vengeance. And hence it is that when God deals againſt ungodly men in ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, he payes them home; becauſe he doth it, as his own expreſſion is, to ſatisfie and <hi>eaſe</hi> himſelf, and not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit or profit them. So that the Lord may ſay, when he is laying on them in the heat of his diſpleaſure, as <hi>Iſay</hi> 1.24. <hi>Ah, I will eaſe me of my enemies!</hi> Now I ſhall eaſe my ſelf of ſuch a drunkard, of ſuch a ſwearer and blaſphemer, of ſuch a lewd prophane and vitious liver that was alwayes vexing me. Now I ſhall hear him ſwear no more, now I ſhall have him rend my wounds no more; I ſhall be preſſed with his ſins no more; I ſhall be quiet now I ſee, I ſhall be eaſed of him forever.</p>
            <p>But now (my brethren) when he deals againſt his own people, it is a greater trouble to him, to make them ſuffer his corrections, then for himſelf to ſuffer their indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and provocations: Nor doth he aime a whit at ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction (for that he hath received from Chriſt to the extremity of Juſtice) but onely at their reformation: So that he gives correction to them, as <hi>phyſick</hi> to recover, and not as <hi>poyſon</hi> to deſtroy. And hence it is, that he deals moderately with them, according as he findes their ſtrength and caſe to be; yet he may not kill, but cure them: He doth ſo chaſtiſe his people, as that he doth not looſe the weakeſt of them by the extremity, or length of the affliction that he layes upon them. The rod of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhall not reſt upon them, leaſt they put forth their hand to evil, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.3. <hi>I will ſift the houſe of Iſrael ſaith the Lord, as corn is ſifted in ſive,</hi> Amos 9.9. <hi>But yet the leaſt grain ſhall not fall upon the earth.</hi> I will not looſe one grain of good wheat, as it is added, &amp;c. and this for clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the former member of the point. It is the manner of the Lord when <hi>he puniſheth</hi> his people to abate and to be very moderate.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:166226:6"/>
            <p>But now (my Brethren) on the otherſide, when <hi>he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers</hi> them, and ſhows them mercy, it is his manner to exceed and to tranſcend all meaſure: Then he takes his full ſcope, and doth not bound and ſtint himſelf as in the former: No he beſtows upon his people ſuperlative and matchleſſe mercies, and ſalvations; he gives them ſuch a deliverance as this, ſuch as hath no parallel, no equall, with which it may be ſampled or compared: Of which that may be ſaid, which the Holy Ghoſt affirmeth of the ſpice, which the Aethiopian Queen preſented to King <hi>Solomon,</hi> 2 Chron. 9.9. There was not any ſuch ſpice; ſo there was never ſuch mercy. In delivering, the Lord ſometimes out-dares himſelf in ſhewing mercy, does rare and ſingular, and extraodinary things, ſuch as he is not wont to doe at other times; ſuch as his people are not able <hi>to expreſſe,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.2. <hi>Who can ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the great and mighty acts of God? who can ſhew forth all his praiſe?</hi> Such as they are not able <hi>to believe;</hi> no, they ſeem like men that dream, as Iſrael did, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 126.1. ſuch as they are not able <hi>to imagine;</hi> he doth abundantly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that they can think, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6.20. nay to go higher yet, ſuch as they are not able (in ſome ſort) <hi>to bear:</hi> As it is ſaid of <hi>Jacob,</hi> when they told him that his ſon <hi>Joſeph</hi> was alive, and that he was made governour over all land of the Aegypt; his <hi>heart fainted,</hi> Gen. 45.26. ſo God ſometimes gives ſuch tranſcendent mercies and deliverances to his people, that their hearts faint within them, they have not ſtrength enough to bear the ſudden fluſh of joy, that comes breaking in upon them. He loadeth them, yea, over loadeth them with benefits, powers out upon them ſuch a heap of mercy as they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſtand under. And whether the deliverance of this Day, were ſuch a ſignal one, ſuch a deliverance as this,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:166226:7"/>
ſuch as you are not able to expreſſe, ſuch as you were not able to believe, nor to imagine, nor to bear almoſt, I leave it to your ſelves (my brethren) to conſider. Ah my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, when you were firſt informed that reliefe was come, and that the Enemy was drawing off the Town, tell me how it fared with you, was not the joy too great for you? too large for thoſe poor hearts of yours to hold? did it not ſtretch them, and dilate them overmuch; ſo that your ſpirits even fainted in you? I know when you reflect upon thoſe daies of old, you will ſeal to this truth; That when the Lord delivers his, and ſhews them mercy, it is his manner to exceed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this he doth for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons; I ſhall name a few of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The condition of his people may be ſuch, that in reſpect of them it may be neceſſary, that God ſtretch him ſelf a little, and go beyond himſelf (I mean his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary courſe) in their deliverance: Unleſſe the Lord be pleaſed to exceed, it will not reach them to be benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to them. As there are <hi>ſins</hi> of divers ſizes and <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of divers ſizes, ſo there are <hi>mercies and deliverances</hi> of divers ſizes too, and one of them muſt be proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the other. If the <hi>affliction</hi> and diſtreſſe be of the large ſize, ſo muſt the <hi>deliverance</hi> be. And hence it is that God ſometimes makes the ſalvation of his people out of meaſure great, becauſe their troubles and afflictions have been ſo: Such a diſtreſſe muſt have ſuch a deliverance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When God delivers his, and ſhews them mercy, it is his manner ſometimes to exceed, &amp;c. that he may make them recompence for their former miſeries. And even as <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when he had dealt ſomewhat roughly and unkindely with his brethren for a while, and uſed them ſo, as if be had forgotten all affection and relation to them; yet in the end, his bowels yearned upon them, ſo that he was not able to contain himſelf; and then he
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:166226:7"/>
opened all his heart, and ſhewed his love more fully to them then he had ever done before: So when the Lord hath dealt a while ſeverely with his people, as they think (though it be alwayes leſſe then their iniquities deſerve) and when he ſees them likely to be ſwallowed up of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and diſpair, then his bowels work within him, and he can hold no longer, but is overcome: And out he breaks into ſuch ſweet and melting declarations of his love, as come not from him at another time; when he perceives his people at the point to ſinck, and to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in their afflictions, he labours to revive and chear them up again, with more then ordinary revelations and diſcoveries of his mercy: He ſees the ſpirit would faile before him, and the ſouls that he hath made; if he ſhould be alwayes wroth, and if he ſhould contend for ever, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.16. And therefore as the loving father when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the child about to ſwound, while he is laying on upon it, preſently lets fall the rod, and fals a kiſſing and embracing of it, and ſpeaking very kindly to it, to fetch life in it again: So deals God with his people, when they faint in their diſtreſſes, and ſinck away under his hand, away he flings the rod, and fals upon their necks, kiſſes away their tears, and makes them know how dear and precious they are to him, notwithſtanding this ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>What was the time that God did ſo abundantly reveal his love to <hi>Hezekiahs</hi> ſoul, as himſelf expreſſeth it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 38. but after that extream affliction, when in ſtead of peace, his ſoul was full of bitternes; ſo that he could not ſpeak in prayer, but chatter'd like a Swallow, and mourned like a Dove. You have heard of <hi>Jobs</hi> affliction, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parallel'd it was in all reſpects, and what end the Lord made, <hi>James</hi> 5.11. and that end was all mercy, God did
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:166226:8"/>
exceed in that buſineſſe, and tranſcend all meaſure: So that me thinks, I ſee <hi>Job</hi> even raviſhed to an extaſie of joy, and I am confident that God had never ſhewed him ſo many choiſe and pregnant tokens of his favour all his life before, as in the end of that affliction. And verily the Lord is never wont to manifeſt ſuch ſingular and extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary mercy to his Church and People, as when they have been dead and buried as it were; when they have been in a remedileſs and deſperate caſe but juſt before, that he may make them full requital to the utmoſt, for all the trouble that hath been upon them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When God delivers his people, it is his manner ſometimes to exceed, &amp;c. that he may lay upon them mighty Obligations. The Lord delights to have his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple much engaged, exceedingly endeared and bound to him; and upon this account ſometimes, he doth over and above for them, that they may ſee how much they are beholding to him, and how much they ow him. That by this means he may oblige and binde them ſtrongly to obedience: And therefore this is made the ſcope and aim of God in all the great things that he did for Iſrael, that they might keep his ſtatutes and obſerve his laws. The Prophet makes a Catalogue before of many rare, choiſe, and precious mercies, which he followed them withall: And then at laſt, he ſhuts up all with this, which ſhews the end of God in all; <hi>That they might keep his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and obſerve his laws,</hi> Pſal. 105. laſt verſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When God delivers his people, it is his manner ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to exceed, &amp;c. that he may raiſe the greater trophie to his own honour, and make his name be remembred in all generations. The Lord ſometimes is pleaſed (my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) to erect pillars, to ſet up monuments of mercy, that the memorial of it may not die for ever. He builds
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:166226:8"/>
a <hi>None-ſuch,</hi> by the greatneſſe of his power, and for the honour of his majeſty: He gives his people ſuch a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, <hi>talis</hi> that you cannot finde a <hi>qualis,</hi> it is not to be matched again. And even as Princes when they have a minde to make their greatneſs known and ſpoken off, are wont to do ſome extraordinary act; ſo God execeds in wayes of kindnes to his people, to this end, that he may appear the more glorious, and that he may ſhew forth to the ages to come, the unſearchable riches of his power and mercy. Its true, that both of them appear, even in his common works, and the leaſt and loweſt of his favors; But in ſuch rare and choice deliverances and ſalvations that tranſcend all meaſure, they ſparkle forth with daz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling luſtre.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Is it the manner of the Lord when he puniſhes his people to abate, &amp;c. Then let us be exact obſervers and admirers of the rich mercy of the Lord both waies: When his work is in <hi>his hand,</hi> let our eyes be in <hi>our head,</hi> and let us diligently look to one ſide and the other, when he <hi>ſtrikes,</hi> how he refrains; when he <hi>ſaves,</hi> how he exceeds. The Prophet <hi>Ezra</hi> very acurately notes them both, <hi>Thou haſt puniſhed us leſſe then our iniquities deſerve, and given us ſuch a deliverance as this?</hi> and we ſhould ſtrive to doe as he did. But alas we uſe to be quite upon the other hand, our manner is to amplifie croſſes, and to deminiſh mercies; when God afflicts, we tell over; when he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, we tell ſhort: We look on our afflictions in a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying glaſſe, which repreſents them more and greater then indeed they are: But when we look on our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we turn the other end, which makes them to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as nothing: When we ſpeak of our diſtreſſes, we ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravate them to the utmoſt; we riſe, we grow in our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as he in the Poet, I am twice, thrice miſerable, nay
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:166226:9"/>
ten times, nay twenty times, nay a hundred times miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. But when we ſpeak of our deliverances, we exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate; we are miſerably ſhort, low and flat: we are quite contrary to God, we exceed where he abates; and we abate where he exceeds: Oh my beloved, let us not be ſo croſs to God, who is ſo kind to us; but let us learn of <hi>Ezra</hi> here, to think and ſpeak of our afflictions in a way of diminution; and on the other ſide, of our ſalvations, in a way of augmentation: And this let me apply a little to the buſineſs of this Day.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Learn to leſſen your afflictions, at leaſt with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to your deſerts: Acknowledge with the Prophet, in my Text, That they were leſſe then your iniquities de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved. Its true, you ſuffered ſharp and bitter things, when you were ſhut up by the Enemies, and many of you more then others: Your <hi>feelings,</hi> I confeſſe, were much, your <hi>fears</hi> were more: But what were all theſe to your <hi>ſins,</hi> if God had dealt in rigour with you? Some of you I ſuppoſe loſt your moſt choice and precious friends, which next to God were deareſt to you in the world; Why, it is a mercy that you have one friend left: Some of you loſt your goods and your eſtates; why, it is a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that you have a peny left: ſome of you loſt your limbs; why, it is a mercy that you did not loſe your lives: ſome of you loſt your houſes, you ſaw them flame and burn till they were raked in their own aſhes; why, it is a mercy that your ſelves are not at this inſtant burning in the flames of Hell it ſelf: Many of you were ſwept away by the Bullet and Sword; why, it is a mercy there was any remnant or eſcaping; that there is one left to tell the news of this deliverance, to magnifie the Lord for it. <hi>In death there is no remembrance of him, in the grave, who can praiſe him?</hi> Where are they that loſt their lives in the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:166226:9"/>
ſieges of this place? they are not here to joyn with us in the ſolemnity and chearfull celebration of this happy Day; to magnifie the Lord with us, and to exalt his name together: ſome of them, were they here no doubt, would be as forward as the beſt of us: But we may ſay to God concerning them, as ſometimes <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did, <hi>The grave cannot praiſe thee, &amp;c. Iſa.</hi> 38.18. or as <hi>Heman</hi> ſometimes did, Pſal. 88.10. <hi>Wilt thou ſhew wonders to the dead, ſhall the dead ariſe and praiſe thee?</hi> No, this is our Prerogative who are preſerved from the grave, and reſcued from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: And it is an extraordinary mercy of the Lord to us, that while others are gone down into the place of ſilence, our lives are lengthened out to ſing his praiſes, and to ſpeak good of his name, to keep another day of of thankfulnes to him, who is the God of our life: O let us ſay, as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did in ſuch a caſe; <hi>The living, the living, they ſhall praiſe thee,</hi> as we do this day. And thus if you ſurvey your ſharpeſt troubles and afflictions; you ſhall finde a mixture and allay of mercy in them, and ſo be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to acknowledge, that God hath puniſhed you <hi>far leſſe then your iniquities deſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Learn hence to amplifie deliverances and ſalvations, to raiſe them to the very height, above expreſſion with the Prophet in my Text, ſuch a deliverance as this, as hath no words to ſet it forth: ſuch as poſterity will not be able to believe: and truly (my Beloved) even ſuch a one was yours; it was a <hi>None-ſuch</hi> in the land, God dealt not ſo with any other people, ſo that it ſhines among de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverances, even as the Moon among the leſſer Stars: Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the great things that the Lord hath done in theſe late years of wonder, and you ſhall finde that the ſalvation of this place was the greateſt of them all, none to be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with it; it had an aſteriſme of mercies in it, body mercies, ſoul mercies, eſtate mercies; which conſpired
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:166226:10"/>
altogether to make it out of meaſure glorious: Among the reſt, this excellency was peculiar to it, that it turned the ſcales of the whol buſines in theſe late wars: Oh my beloved, look round about this rare deliverance, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie it all the wayes that you can think upon; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how you prized it, when you were pleading for your lives, before the Lord, in the day of your diſtreſſe, what you would have done or given to be aſſured of a delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, from that cruel death, which with amazing thoughts you looked for, when you were ready to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by an enemy, whoſe rage and malice was boiled up to the heigth againſt you, &amp;c. who would in probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty have ſpared neither age nor ſex; I ſay, remember how you prized it then, and do not let the price to fall again: Then it was valued at the higheſt, when you were reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after it with fainting ſouls; now it is nothing with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of you: Oh loath your ſelves, for this baſenes, and make it your great buſines of this Day, to raiſe and to keep up the price of this incomparable mercy, to make the moſt of ſuch a rare deliverance as this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. It is the manner of the Lord when he puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his people, to abate and to be very moderate; when he delivers them and ſhews them mercy, to exceed and to tranſcend all meaſure; and do we finde that he hath ſo exceeded as in other mercies, ſo ſpecially in the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of this Day. Then let us ſeriouſly conſider, what a weight of duty lyes upon us, and how we ought to tranſcend and to exceed in our returns to God again. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it (brethren) ordinary matters will not ſerve the turn; as God hath done more for us, ſo he muſt have more from us then from any other people: we muſt do ſingular and extraordinary things; if he exceed in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, we muſt accordingly exceed in duty, there muſt be ſome proportion of the one unto the other; we muſt ſtrive to render to him according to the benefits
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:166226:10"/>
that he hath done us, and to come up as near as it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his meaſure; ſuch a deliverance muſt have ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, and here to pitch upon particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such a deliverance muſt have ſuch a remembrance, it muſt have ſome memoriall anſwerable to it. As for our ſelves (my brethren) we muſt ingrave it on our hearts, and keep a Regiſter of all the mercies that concurred in it. As <hi>David</hi> had an inventory of the Gold and Silver that he provided for the temple, but the iron and the braſſe he numbreth not, becauſe it was without weight, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22.14. So though we cannot reckon all the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Lord, his dayly, and his hourly mercies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe indeed they are without number, yet we muſt be exact in numbring and ſetting down his Golden and his Silver mercies. Such a deliverance as this, with all the circumſtances of it, muſt not be forgotten by us.</p>
            <p>And yet this is not all my berthren: we muſt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keep theſe rare and extraordinary mercies in our minds our ſelves, but we muſt take ſome courſe that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may be mindfull of them, and that while the world laſts, that the Lord may have his glory kept afoot in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ages, A duty much commended to us in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, upon ſuch occaſions. When God had wrought a great ſalvation for his people Iſrael, <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded them to write a ſong, and to teach it to their children, that it might be a witneſſe for the Lord againſt them, <hi>viz.</hi> if they ſhould prove unthankfull, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.19. <hi>When the Lord ſhall build up Sion, he ſhall appear in glory,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.16. And what then, muſt they keep one day of thankfulneſſe, and ſo an end? No there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what further to be done, <hi>this ſhall be written for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations to come, and the people that ſhal be created ſhall praiſe the Lord.</hi> Indeed there is an Ordinance of the high Court of heaven, to this purpoſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.5. <hi>He appointed a Law
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:166226:11"/>
in Iſrael, which he did command our fathers,</hi> and what did he command our fathers? <hi>That they ſhould make the praiſes of the Lord his ſtrength and wondrous works, that he had done, that they ſhould make them known unto their children, and to the generation that was yet to come.</hi> And therfore I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you (my beloved) let us think upon it, let us inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to perpetuate the praiſe of God, let us uſe ſome means or other to tranſmit it to poſterity, to make ſucceeding generations know what God had done for this Land, for this place, that he may have the glory of it <hi>as long as the ſun &amp; moon indureth.</hi> Brethren we have a great task in this kind, we have very much to do, becauſe the Lord hath done ſo much: truly I think, that there was never any ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration that had ſuch a weight of duty lay upon them. It was the ſaying of a wiſeman, that troubleſom times were good for the writer, &amp; il for the liver, he that lives in them ſhall have ſorrow enough: He that writes of them ſhall have matter enough; &amp; certainly theſe times of ours, yield matter of tranſmiſsion to ſucceeding generations more then any former ages. Let us take care as much as lies in us, that nothing be loſt, not a ſcrap of any thing that God hath done for this Land, or for this Town, in plague, and in the ſieges, but that it may be all conveyed down intire and whole and undiminiſht to following ages; that the generations that are yet to come may praiſe the Lord; And to this end I ſhall ſet before you two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. God will be a gainer by it. Alas (my brethren) it is little glory, we can bring him in our ſelves, and in our own time, if we ſhould ſpend all our dayes in praiſing him, they are ſhort and will be done upon the ſudden. But if we can take courſe that all the generations, that are yet to come, ſhall praiſe him for the mercy which we have received, as long as the world laſts: this will be a great advantage, and truly if we love him, &amp; be affected
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:166226:11"/>
with his mercy as we ought to be; we will endeavour what we can to raiſe, and to advance the little tribute of glory and thankſgiving, which he is like to have among us, after ſo many rich and precious favours heapt upon us. And ſeeing we our ſelves who have received ſo much, can pay ſo little; we will be ſo honeſt yet, to charge our heirs, with what is comming from us to the Lord. And even as <hi>David</hi> layes a tax on all Nations, all Angels, all Creatures, to come in and to attribute what they can to the praiſes of the Lord, ſo we will lay a tax on all ſucceeding generations, while the world continues, that God may not loſe all; but that he may in ſome proportion have the glory that is due unto his name.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Succeeding generations will be gainers by it too; me thinks the Prophet mentions it as advantage and priviledge to them of thoſe times, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.1. <hi>We have heard with our ears, O God, our fathers have told us, what works thou didſt in their dayes, &amp; in the times of old:</hi> He ſeems to be affected very much with the relation; And truly (my beloved) it may be very beneficiall to after ages, to be acquainted with the work of God, to know what he hath done in former times; it will bind them and engage them, to walk in ſome proportion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to them; or if they do not, it will be a witneſſe for the Lord againſt them: As <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.19. It will teſtifie what God hath done, and what they ought to do; that they will not be able to be quiet, if they be unthankfull. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech you (my beloved) let us think of ſomething in this kinde or other, after ſuch a rare deliverance. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord of old, were wont to ſet up monuments of the great works of God, as <hi>Jacobs El Elohe Iſrael,</hi> Gen. 33.20. <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Jehovah Niſſi, Exod.</hi> 17.5. and <hi>Samuels Eben Ezer,</hi> 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.12. And ſhall there be no monument of ſuch aſtrange ſalvation as ours was? No memoriall of ſuch a deliverance as this? Truly (my Brethren) if you will ſet up ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of it, ſome work of Piety or Charity, to be a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:166226:12"/>
ſtranding monument of this deliverance; you would doe ſomething worthy of your ſelves, and of the Lord who hath been ſo gratious to you.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Such a deliverance muſt have ſuch a celebration, as is anſwerable to it; and truly for the outward part, I muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge you exceed in this place; you do well that you triumph and Shout, Ring, make Fires, and feed upon the Creatures, and that liberally too: but yet you muſt not think that this is the main buſineſſe (for bodily exerciſe profiteth little) nay which is worſe, you muſt not ſuffer it to be a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance to the main buſineſſe. Truly (my brethren) I have obſerved heretofore, that there hath been too much fleſh, too little ſpirit, in the obſervation of this Day. The bodily and fleſhly part, hath been very high indeed, but the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all part which God alone regardeth, for it ſelf, hath been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry low and flat. Mens Tables have been better furniſhed, and their bodies finer dreſt, but for their prayers and their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in their Families, or in their Cloſets, they have been either none at all, or all one as at other times. There are too many of us, who have taken too much liberty upon ſuch dayes as theſe, in a carnall fleſhly way, and have been over-charged, and made unfit for ſpiritual ſervice: I ſay, as the Apoſtle, Such rejoycing is not good; rejoycing is good, but ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing is not good. Oh my beloved, I beſeech you, let not the mercy of the Lord have a return of ſin inſtead of a return of praiſe; yea under the ſhew and colour of praiſe: do not make this bleſſed day an occaſion to the fleſh; let this be ſuch a feaſt as follows a holy convocation, and is agreeable and ſuitable to it. While we are at it, let us do as birds do, ſip a little and look up, take the creature moderately, and and look up with thankfulneſſe, to the God of our mercies; let us rejoice with trembling, tremble to ſin againſt God on the day of our rejoicing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Such a deliverance muſt have ſuch a Reformation, as is
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:166226:12"/>
anſwerable to it, a choice and ſingular and extraordinary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, ſuch a one as is not to be matcht again in all the Land. As there was no deliverance like ours, ſo there muſt be no Reformation like ours, it muſt be high and full, beyond any other people, that it may be ſaid of us as of <hi>Joſiah</hi> once, with reference to the exact and glorious Reformation that he made, <hi>like unto him there was no King before him, nor after him aroſe there any ſuch.</hi> So there was never any people like to <hi>Taunton</hi> for thankfulneſſe and for obedience, nor after them ſhall there be any ſuch, that they that look upon us, and obſerve us, may ſay to us as they did to the vertuous woman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.29. <hi>Many people have done vertuouſly, but you have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled them all.</hi> Never did God exceed in mercy to a People, as he did to <hi>Taunton,</hi> and never did a people excell in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as they have done. Ah my beloved, think upon it after the Lord hath given us ſuch a deliverance as this, ſhall we again break his commandements? as you have it in my Text. Shall we do it, who have been ſo ſignally delivered by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked arm of God? and ſhall we do it in the ſelf ſame kind, that we have done in former times? As <hi>Ezra</hi> ſpeaks expreſly here, <hi>ſhall we again break thy Commandements, by joyning in affinity with the people of the Land?</hi> after this, ſhall we return to our old corruptions, and our wonted wayes again? ſhall thoſe which have been heretofore the ſins of <hi>Taunton,</hi> be the ſins of <hi>Taunton</hi> ſtill? Beloved, look a little back upon your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer practiſes, and ſee what alterations this ſignall mercy of the Lord hath made among you, eſpecially thoſe which are the publick known and noted; evil of this place. Not to ſpeak of pride or covetouſneſſe, or Sabboth prophanation. Some ſay the Taverns and the Alehouſes, were never ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented, that Drunkenneſſe was never ſo common, and ſo rife amongſt us, as it is at this day. Ah (my beloved) what will become of this in the latter end? why verily if God be ſtill provoked thus, he will exceed in wrath as he hath done
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:166226:13"/>
in mercy, he will be angry till he hath conſumed us, that there will be no remnant nor eſcaping: He ſaved a remnant laſt, but now he will deſtroy that remnant too, and make an utter deſolation.</p>
            <p>Oh (my beloved) let us who are before the Lord this day, remember, that we are the remainder that are left, the reſidue that are eſcaped from the late judgements that have been upon this place, to tell the world how ſharp God hath been to others, and how mercifull to us. And therefore let the fear of the great God of heaven be upon us the remainder of our dayes, let us conſider why he hath preſerved us, not to be <hi>inſtruments</hi> of his diſhonor, but <hi>monuments</hi> of his praiſe: That preſent and ſucceeding generations, may ſay of us, as the Prophet did of <hi>Iſrael, Deut.</hi> 33.29, Happy art thou O <hi>Taunton,</hi> who is like to thee, O people ſaved of the Lord: None have been like to thee in mercy and ſalvation, and none are like to thee in holineſſe and Reformation.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
